A Guide to the Thursday Morning Garden Club Collection, 1965-2010
Virginia Room, Fairfax County Public Library
The Thursday Morning Garden Club Collection, 1965-2010
Fairfax County Public Library
MSS 05-47
3.5 linear feet
The Thursday Morning Garden Club Collection consists of 3.5 linear feet and spans the years 1965-2010. The collection contains club yearbooks, correspondence, meeting minutes, financial records, and scrapbooks of photos, newspaper clippings, and event programs.
Thursday Morning Garden Club
Administrative Information
Access Restrictions
None
Acquisition Information
Donated by Sandra Butcher, President of the Thursday Morning Garden Club, in September 2011
Historical and Biographical Information
The Thursday Morning Garden Club was named for their meeting time on the third Thursday of every month. The club was formed in 1965 in the Potomac Hills subdivision in McLean, Virginia and disbanded in 2010 due to decreasing membership. Throughout its history, the club held monthly meetings with presentations on gardening-related topics or tours of local and regional gardens, and held several social events throughout the year for the enjoyment of its members. The club was active in the Potomac Hills community, sponsoring the neighborhood Christmas decorating contest, supporting efforts to develop a recreational park in the Potomac Hills area, implementing neighborhood beautification projects, and supporting a number of organizations with charitable donations. The club’s last official activities included the installation and dedication of a bench in the Adams-Nelson-Sewell-Hirst Cemetery in the Potomac Hills subdivision in November 2010 and donation of the club’s remaining balance to local charity Share, Inc.
Scope and Content
The Thursday Morning Garden Club Collection consists of 3.5 linear feet and spans the years 1965-2010. The collection contains club yearbooks, correspondence, meeting minutes, financial records, and scrapbooks of photos, newspaper clippings, and event programs. Subjects include the history and events of the Thursday Morning Garden Club and the Marie Butler Leven Preserve.
Series 1: Administrative Papers, 1968-2010, Box 1
This series contains yearbooks of the Thursday Morning Garden Club featuring club members, officers, committees, by-laws, meetings and events, and copies of gardening-related newspaper articles and tips; President’s Books featuring annotated meeting minutes, membership and committee member lists, select correspondence, and the annual President’s Report; gardening resources; records of meeting attendance; records of club parties; materials from the National Capital Area Federation of Garden Clubs, Inc.; duties of club officers and chairladies; records related to community projects, such as preservation of Anoria park land (later named Marie Butler Leven Preserve), Marie Butler Leven Preserve tree tagging, Marie Butler Leven Preserve Master Plan, installation and maintenance of the Potomac Hills neighborhood sign, and the Potomac Hills Christmas decoration competition; and records related to club disbandment and installation and dedication of a bench in the Adams-Nelson-Sewell-Hirst Cemetery. Also included is a DVD of the cemetery bench dedication ceremony.
Series 2: Correspondence, 1966-2009, Box 1
This series includes copies of correspondence to and from the club, including letters for coordinating event logistics, conveying charitable donations, corresponding with local agencies regarding community projects or issues of concern to the club, and informing or querying club members about club issues.
Series 3: Financial Records, 1965-2009, Box 1
This series includes receipts for club expenses, treasurer’s reports showing monthly income and expenses, cancelled checks, lists of charitable donations, and checking account statements.
Series 4: Meeting Minutes, 1965-2009, Box 1
This series includes minutes of monthly club meetings and annual Executive Board meetings, including select President’s Reports.
Series 4: Scrapbooks, 1956-2004, Box 2
This series includes five scrapbooks with photos from club events as well as lists of club officers, event programs, and newspaper clippings.
Adjunct Descriptive Data
None
None
Index Terms
Marie Butler Leven Preserve (McLean, Va.); McLean (Va.) - History; Potomac Hills (McLean, Va.); Thursday Morning Garden Club (McLean, Va.)
Container List
- Series 1: Administrative Papers, 1966-2010
  - Yearbooks, 1968-1974, 1968-1974 (Box 1, Folder 1)
  - Yearbooks, 1974-1979, 1974-1979 (Box 1, Folder 2)
  - Yearbooks, 1979-1982, 1979-1982 (Box 1, Folder 3)
  - Yearbooks, 1982-1986, 1982-1986 (Box 1, Folder 4)
  - Yearbooks, 1986-1989, 1986-1989 (Box 1, Folder 5)
  - Yearbooks, 1990-1994, 1990-1994 (Box 1, Folder 6)
  - Yearbooks, 2003-2007, 2003-2007 (Box 1, Folder 7)
  - President’s Book, 1974-1975, 1974-1975 (Box 1, Folder 8)
  - President’s Book, 1975-1976, 1975-1976 (Box 1, Folder 9)
  - Gardening Resources, Undated (Box 1, Folder 10)
  - Potomac Hills Street Tree Planting Recommendations, Undated (Box 1, Folder 11)
  - Membership Application, Undated (Box 1, Folder 12)
  - Potomac Hills Christmas Decoration Competition, 1963, 1966-1969 (Box 1, Folder 13)
  - Meeting Attendance, 1968-1977 (Box 1, Folder 14)
  - Anoria Park Land and Kirby Road Widening, 1969-1978 (Box 1, Folder 15)
  - Potomac Hills Sign, 1970-1972 (Box 1, Folder 16)
  - Marie Butler Leven Preserve Tree Tagging, 1971-1977 (Box 1, Folder 17)
  - Parties, 1972-1975 (Box 1, Folder 18)
  - Materials of National Capital Area Federation of Garden Clubs, Inc., 1976-1981 (Box 1, Folder 19)
  - Duties of Officers and Chairladies, 1981-1982 (Box 1, Folder 20)
  - Marie Butler Leven Preserve Master Plan, 1985-1987 (Box 1, Folder 21)
  - Club Disbandment and Cemetery Bench Dedication [includes DVD], 2009-2010 (Box 1, Folder 22)
  - Adams-Nelson-Sewell-Hirst Cemetery, 2009-2010 (Box 1, Folder 23)
- Series 2: Correspondence, 1966-2009
  - Correspondence, 1966 December-1972 June (Box 1, Folder 24)
  - Correspondence, 1973 October-2009 September (Box 1, Folder 25)
- Series 3: Financial Records, 1965-2009
  - Receipts and Expenses, 1965 November-1978 April (Box 1, Folder 26)
  - Receipts and Expenses, 1995 July-2002 November (Box 1, Folder 27)
  - Receipts and Expenses, 2007 November-2010 November (Box 1, Folder 28)
  - Treasurer’s Reports, 1965 November-1974 September (Box 1, Folder 29)
  - Treasurer’s Reports, 1974 October-1982 May (Box 1, Folder 30)
  - Treasurer’s Reports, 1997 September-2000 September (Box 1, Folder 31)
  - Treasurer’s Reports, 2000 September-2004 March (Box 1, Folder 32)
  - Treasurer’s Reports, 2004 September-2009 October (Box 1, Folder 33)
  - Cancelled Checks, 1969-1978 (Box 1, Folder 34)
  - Donations, 1987-2002 (Box 1, Folder 35)
  - Checking Account Statements, 2000-2003 (Box 1, Folder 36)
- Series 4: Meeting Minutes, 1965-2009
  - Meeting Minutes, 1965 December-1971 May (Box 1, Folder 37)
  - Meeting Minutes, 1971 August-1975 May (Box 1, Folder 38)
  - Meeting Minutes, 1975 June-1977 May (Box 1, Folder 39)
  - Meeting Minutes, 1981 September-1982 May (Box 1, Folder 40)
  - Meeting Minutes, 1982 August-1986 May (Box 1, Folder 41)
  - Meeting Minutes, 1986 June-1991 May (Box 1, Folder 42)
  - Meeting Minutes, 1991 September-1996 June (Box 1, Folder 43)
  - Meeting Minutes, 1996 September-2009 October (Box 1, Folder 44)
- Series 5: Scrapbooks, 1966-2007
  - Scrapbook, 1966-1985, 1966-1985 (Box 2)
  - Scrapbook, 1982-1990, 1982-1990 (Box 2)
  - Scrapbook, 2004-2005, 2004-2005 (Box 2)
  - Scrapbook, 2000-2001, 2000-2001 (Box 2)
  - Scrapbook, 2006-2007, 2006-2007 (Box 2)